[Music]
hey welcome back so today is day three
of the Tinkercad camp we're gonna be
working with circuits again today but
today the code that we type is gonna be
text-based coding
I'm here with my trusty camper as always
McKinley are you ready to go today
McKinley yeah are you excited to do tech
space programming how are your typing
skills working on it that's fair alright
so we are going to be typing today so
you probably will have to pause the
video some because I typed super fast
right and I'll try to like delay so I'm
here and there but don't be surprised at
all if there's times where you kind of
need to like pause things so here's the
the circuit that we're making today so
it's using something called an RGB LED
and we'll talk more about that but it
stands for a red green blue it's kind of
like a single pixel unlike your phone or
TV or something like that so where me
coding that up and we're going to be
learning about some of the main things
in coding so we're gonna be learning
about functions we're gonna be learning
about variables we're gonna be learning
about if statements and I'm gonna also
kind of sneak in for loops at the end so
really it's not that the things we're
building or that amazing I'm it's that
the skills that we're learning with like
if statements and things like that so
this light can either flash or be steady
on that's what we're gonna be doing so
right now it's steady on now it's
flashing and then you can change the
color with these potentiometers so if I
made it red and green it would turn
bright yellow if I take down the yellow
amount it turns this red or I turn up
the blue it kind of turns purple right
so that's kind of the goal so to start
things off go ahead and open a new
Tinkercad circuit so log into Tinkercad
hopefully you got that down and click on
create new circuit and we'll get started
all right so my projects up it picks a
crazy name to start with and we need to
come up with a name for today's project
there's no like good name so I think I'm
just gonna give mine a very generic name
I'm going to call it CW C which stands
for connecting with code 2020 right here
day three not really a great name but I
didn't really come up with a good name I
said that's what it is I guess I could
have called it like learning about
functions and learning about variables
and blah blah blah blah so the first
thing we want to do is we want to add a
breadboard you can drag to bring the
breadboard over but I actually preferred
a single click on the breadboard and
then it just kind of like follows my
mouse around until I click a second time
to place it you'll find that with
Tinkercad they usually do that where you
click once and then you move and you
click again they actually did that a lot
more than dragging so the first thing I
want to do is I want to rotate my board
so it's kind of like sitting here next
thing I want to do is I want to grab on
uno so I single clicked on uno now I'm
not touching anything and I'm actually
going to rotate it before I place this
right so I rotate and then I click a
second time to place it so this
configuration is what you use a lot when
you're kind of learning you know this
type of material and there's a lot of
boards that are set up like this I
didn't bother bring my physical board
today because we're going to do
everything on the simulation today so
the first thing that you do want to do
if you have a setup like this is you
want to connect the power and ground
from your Arduino over to the breadboard
and what I'm going to do is I'm going to
put power and ground in kind of high up
on the board so I'm going to connect my
power to row 6 the red line that's right
next to row 6 and you can click on the
5v over here and then you can click on
the the plus rail really you can put it
anywhere in the plus rail I put it in
row 6 because I know that's where the
spacing is network out if you don't care
about pretty you can just stick it right
on there and be done if you do care
about pretty what you can do is you can
double click and add some bins to your
wire and if you want to you can double
click and you can add these pretty bins
to kind of like make it look a certain
way another thing you can do if you want
if you can change the color of wires you
can click on them and you can like
select it here or there's some shortcut
keys that you can memorize so to would
it just turned out red I think I'm going
to do is I'm going to connect Browns so
I'm going to kind of put it right below
it and if you want to you can make these
things
see bins like while you place the wire
and then here I'll just press the number
one to put it in place trying to do it
when I make the wire is okay but I
actually kind of prefer to do it after
that I can street and everything up the
way I want McKinley did you make nice
pretty bins and yours or did you just
shoot them across today should you shoot
some across and that's just five all
right so now let's add some other things
so what I want to add next is I want to
add an RGB LED you can look for an RGB
LED in here it's actually not too far
down or you can always type em it'll
it'll search for your right to make it
easier to find so I'm going to take an
RGB LED and I'm going to rotate it so
that it sticks in the very top four rows
over on the left-hand side I
intentionally put it over on the
left-hand side because by putting it
there are some things are going to be
easier for me and then by the way I just
click on the X to clear off my search
the next thing I want to do is I want to
add resistors to certain spots of this
LEDs so there's four rows on this LED if
you hover over the legs they're called
green blue cathode
I'm written probably all those words
make sense except for Cap'n right
cathode is another another word for
something that needs to be at the lower
voltage potential right so in this case
it needs to go to ground so connect this
line that has the cathode on it to
ground and my wire was black because the
last wire I'd created was black so the
way this RGB LED works is if you could
zoom way in on it it's actually three
LEDs in the same package one that shines
red light one that shines green light
and the other that shines blue blue
light this is how pixels like on your
computer monitor right now work your
computer monitor probably has literally
like thousands millions of different
pixels and we're working with one pixel
right and the neat thing about RGB is
you can actually make any color using
just RGB lights so those three can make
any color there's a lot of light Theory
things that we could talk about but it
would probably make this video get too
long if I explain it all so you can look
up more about RGB light
just know that's how it works so the
next thing we want to do is since these
ROI are three LEDs we're going to need
three resistors so we talked about
resistors last time so what I'm going to
do is I'm going to take a resistor I'm
going to rotate it and I'm going to pop
it onto my board now I'll see if your
memory is is really really good
the default resistor was one kiloohm but
I want to change that to regular ohms
and I want to type in a number here to
see any chance you remember the number
yes what is it 330 that's correct and
the 330 ohm resistor is what makes an
LED have the correct amount of
brightness too small and it would be
brighter but it might blow up and too
big it'll be dimmer
so 330 is what I need now I actually
need three of these resistors and I
could drag over one at a time and change
them but this is actually a shortcut if
you just click on the existing resistor
and you hit control C and then control V
that's copy/paste and then it'll just
kind of make a duplicate for you once
you spend a lot of time on computers
copy paste control-c control-v you'll
use those all the time so copy paste
that top resistor and give me two more
so now we've got one for the green one
for the blue and one down here for the
red now we need to control these three
lines from the Arduino Uno so let's go
ahead and draw the wires and then I'll
kind of show you what all we've got this
top one is green the second one is blue
and the bottom one is red I actually
want to take red and I'll connect it I
couldn't remember what pinouts going to
and I'll connect it to pin nine so I'm
going to connect it to pin 9 over here
and since it's for the red component I'm
going to switch it red and then because
I couldn't stand not to do it I'm going
to bend the wire
so that it is a kind of a little easier
to see cool so I'm going to kind of make
it like that so I'm kind of see that
it's going to the nine next up I want
the green wire so the green wires on top
here so I'm going to click on this green
wire and it's gonna go to pen ten so I'm
going to make it kind of go around here
and then two ten ten and then I want it
to be green green is the keyboard
shortcut five and then the last one is
blue and I want blue to go to pen eleven
now why did I put them in these spots
and blue is shortcut key seven so I put
these in crazy spots right but they are
there in illogical spots if you look at
the nine ten eleven you'll notice that
they all have this like little tilde
next to them and this little tilde means
that this pin can be used as a PWM
outlet so I used the top three pins the
app Tilda's and I put them in order of
red green blue because that's how I
think about these LEDs now it is
interesting that the actual physical LED
is not in order it goes red cathode blue
green Tinkercad must have thought that
was the most common way to actually get
one of these like in your hand so they
tried to do it with like what you could
physically buy it turns out that what
you can physically buy actually is in
order these days but take your kid still
has the traditional great so if I was
following the the current if I wanted to
turn on red here's what happens I would
bring pen 9 high and would pin nine high
power would flow through this rail it
would flow through this resistor and
that resistor is important is that limit
sumit current that is so that's just the
right brightness I'm light up the LED it
does a diode drop to cause the light and
then all the LEDs come back down through
ground and then that ground flows back
into my board so it doesn't look like
loop on the circuit but it is and it's
important that anytime you have current
flowing there's a loop someone right
that makes sense
all right now in order to see this we're
gonna write some code what we're going
to be doing today is all text-based
except for this very first thing so
we're going to do one thing with blocks
and then we're gonna move into text and
not look back
so with blocks that should be the
default editor there's some code on here
don't want any of that code
take it all dump it in the trash now
what I want to do is I want to take this
third command it says set pin and then
it picks some number three in this case
to zero now this command is different
than the one that says set pin zero to
high and it's different because this one
you can give a number from zero to 255
for how much you want right so if you
wanted to turn it all the way on you
would say 255 if you wanted to turn it
all the way off you'd say zero if you
wanted to turn it halfway on you'd say
127 do you get the idea so here's what I
want to do I want to turn on red all the
way in order to turn on red all the way
I need pin nine because it's connected
to the red wire and then I want to bring
two more over as well for ten and eleven
and now for this very first test I want
to turn on just red so I'm saying hey
turn on red full blast but nothing for
green and nothing for blue so when I hit
start simulation what should happen is
my LED should turn on fully red let's
change it let's play some other colors
let's say we wanted to do fully green
you can test all these or you can just
watch mine fully green would be 0 255 0
I'm sure you can guess what fully blue
would be it's zero 0 255 and now here's
the interesting thing you can mix colors
as much as you would like so for example
if I added some red to my blue I would
turn it a light shade of purple so
there's a light purple if I added all
the colors together
so there was 255 to divide 285 it would
be white if I did none of the colors 0 0
0 it would essentially be black which is
off that's the least exciting one and
then there are some other interesting
color combinations this one I think is
always fun red and green they go
together and make yellow now this is
light addition not light subtraction so
if you had paints and you mix like red
paint and green paint together
that uses a system called light
subtraction the the light you see is one
of our bounces off of there and it
wouldn't be yellow but with light
addition that's like somebody's shining
in a red flashlight at you and shine in
a green flashlight at you and of those
two like mixed together perfectly that
does create you so light addition is
different about subtraction it's I kind
of sort of make sense McKinley ho little
all right you'll get you'll get better
no time so now what I want to do is I
want to transition to text so right now
I can hit blocks plus text and it will
show me the text for these blocks now
it's interesting to look at there's some
code that happen and set up it sets up
all these things to be outputs and then
there's some things that happen down
inside the loop and it uses a command
called analog right pen 9 so that kind
of makes sense 255 and the last thing I
had in here was 9 10 11 255 255 0 and
you can see the code that gets generated
so hopefully that that makes sense now
what we're going to do is instead of
looking at both we're gonna jump
straight into text so we're gonna only
do text from this moment forward so
click on text it warns you big big bold
letters
that your blocks are gonna go away once
you go text you don't come back so
that's fine so we're gonna say continue
so now from this moment forward are
gonna be coding in text which would be
fun
the program still works the same as it
did before it's currently yellow if I
wanted to switch it back to red I just
have to change the text so to 5500 I run
it and it works with text just as well
and so now we're gonna start learning
about things using text with the same
simple circuit the first thing we're
going to learn about is functions so
what are functions functions are little
chunks of code that work together to
solve some problem and this chunk of
code right here analog right 2 9 10 and
11 they work together to cause red so
anytime something works together it
could become a function so let's do this
type with me and then I'll explain it so
type this type void which is kind of a
weird word red parenthesis parenthesis
open curly brace and then a blank line
and then closing curly brace the curly
braces by the way they're under keyboard
you have to hold down shift the title
you'll find them of you you don't hold
down shift you get a square bracket if
you do hold down shift you get a curly
brace so now what I want to do is I want
to cut cut is control X those three
lines and paste them control V down
inside here so now what I've done is
I've made a little function that I can
call anytime I want so now if I want to
make the light be red I have a function
that I can call to do that so let's go
ahead and practice calling it so let's
do this type in the word red parenthesis
parenthesis semicolon and what we've
done here is we've written a function
red and we've called the function from
our main so this code should work
exactly the same as it did before
we've just instead of like having this
code like right inside of the loop
instead we've got a function called read
and then this line of code right here is
calling the function read to make it run
it's good by the way there's a couple
functions on here one is the function
setup it's called under the hood to do
the setup and then there's another
function loop and loop is
all and then as soon as Luke finishes
the system like under the hood it calls
the loop function again and you can do
whatever you want in here so let's go
ahead and run it and make sure that it
still shows up red it does which is good
let's practice making another function I
see if you can pause the video and do
this on your own make a function called
green and then instead of calling red
you can comment out red with slash slash
instead create a function called green
and then call your function green from
the main you see if you can make that
happen
all right so I've got mine ready here so
I call the function green and down here
I made the function green I copy pasted
red and just changed and then notice
that green as a zero for the red value
and a 255 for the green value now I'm
gonna run it to see if it works so I run
it and mine does work but I also want to
show you what happened to be making
error so coding is very very picky right
so for example let's say on this line
where I call green I had left off the
semicolon if I leave off the semicolon
my code is invalid it won't compile now
then you're like oh couldn't they figure
out what you meant and so I go no that's
not how it works right so if I tried to
run the simulation now it's gonna show
up with a bunch of red tests right and
this red like you see red everywhere
your eyes like shut down oh my god it's
terrible
it tells me that there's some error now
the error it says is on this line delay
10 semicolon do you think the error is
really on that line cissie's it really
on that line you know so this happened
to all the time in code it is often the
line before where it says the errors
because that's where you actually made
the mistake it's just the compiler
didn't it was able to kind of like
handle it for a little while and then it
exploded later I was just missing a
semicolon up there now there's lots of
errors that can be made on if you can
figure it out please do figure it out
but know that if it's really a stumper
the zoom office hours are here to help I
so then I've got two functions
red and green I want to make one more
function I'll just do this with you I
called off so what I do is well first I
got to stop my simulation I'm gonna show
you how I made mine is I just copied red
so now I've got a copy of Reds and I've
got red red it'd be bad to have two and
I'm gonna change this one to off right
and for off I just want to take all of
the red the green of the blue values and
make them zero zero and zero and now
what I could do just for fun is I could
call my functions so maybe I'll call red
I'll delay for a second and then maybe
I'll call off and I'll delay for a
second and then this loop is gonna
continue to get called by the way
there's a delay ten down here which
doesn't really do much
it says minor delay to improve the
performance of the simulation it doesn't
do any harm so I'm gonna leave it down
there but it also doesn't really do
anything useful I'm speaking which I'm
gonna go and clean up some of my
comments so I'm gonna go ahead and
delete my off you can leave comments in
there if you want but but they're not
really necessary so I thought I just but
what you can do here is you can see how
you can mix the functions you write with
the functions that are like built-in so
I'm calling my function red to turn on
the red light and then I'm calling a
built-in function called delay delay
causes some number of like millisecond
delays here it's causing a thousand
milliseconds thousand milliseconds one
second so it should be on and then just
wait for a second and then turn off and
then just wait for a second so if I run
this right now you can see that it
should turn red for a second and then
off for a second cool and if you wanted
it to flash faster I mean you can pick
the flashing speed but you could change
that number 1000 to a smaller number and
that would make it flash fast right so
if I did 500 there
I would be 500 milliseconds which would
be like half a second on out and second
off and so it would just kind of flash
faster you can leave the code at
whatever state you would like I'm gonna
leave mine right here I'll warn you that
some things we're gonna do later are
gonna kind of build on this so if you
wanted to make it crazy that's fine
but make sure it's not too crazy because
we are going to build on this so this is
the first of our topics functions and
now we're gonna learn about some more
more things in programming who actually
I want to do more with functions first
let's do this this will be fun let's
make a function that receives arguments
so you see how this delay received an
argument it received this argument of
500 and that told it a function do use
this argument to do your job and you'll
notice that there's 10 motive here it
has two arguments you can pass arguments
in two functions let's create a function
that receives arguments now normally I
would put mine at the very bottom on my
page but I'll tell you what just to kind
of keep all my functions together I'm
gonna put it right below the loop it
doesn't matter where you put your
function Arduino is really nice about
letting me put them in order let's make
a function called RGB sometimes whatever
I name my functions they use really long
names but I'm trying to keep it short I
just because I know that typing isn't as
easy for everybody right now
RGB this is my new function it's going
to receive some parameters it's gonna
receive an integer number called our
arms gonna represent how much red do you
want it's gonna receive an integer
number called G and it's gonna probably
no surprise receive an integer number
called V after you type those you have
to type the opening curly brace and then
the closing curly brace
now this opening curly brace and closing
curly brace these are because the
language we're using is the C
programming language
technically it's C++ but as far as
you're concerned it's it's C so you're
learning the programming language you
see if you're using
like Python or Java or JavaScript they
might have different rules for the
syntax but you just kind of have to get
used to the syntax whatever language you
learn i I know literally like 20
different languages and it's not hard to
jump from language to language computer
programming language it's not not like
German but they just all have their own
little sin taxes but they all have a lot
of the same concepts so here's this
function and it receives three arguments
RG and B before we even write the
insides of this function let's call it
and see kind of how it works here's what
I want to do right now I'm always making
my light be red I'm gonna switch it to
use my function RGB and what I'm gonna
do is I don't know maybe I'll use a fair
amount of red I just kind of picked a
number I did 180 so a fair amount of red
I know
blue I should use do something to make
it not be the same red so I chose to do
a fair amount of red so like 2/3 of red
or something like that
no green and then an equal amount of
blue as I did red McKinlay do you know
what an equal amount of red and blue
with no green would cause purple she's
on it so right now this is gonna cause
purple now if I were to run my program
right now it would do nothing because it
would call this function it would pass
in 180 + 0 + 180 but then my function is
blind right so we need to write the
inside of this function because I'm lazy
it's going to be similar to these other
functions so I'm going to do a ctrl C
and a ctrl V to kind of type most of it
now the one that I copied from was off
right but here's what I want to change
and off is set those three values to 0 0
and 0 now I want to set them to our G
and B and so this is an important
concept that for how functions work so
you call the function or G B you pass in
180 0 180 and then the computer goes and
runs that function and the
you for our is whatever you passed in
first which is the 180 G is second which
is the zero and then B is the last one
which happens to also be a 180 so if I
run this program now it should flash
with the purple LED and sure enough I
run it and it's this cool purple color
now just for fun I want you to make up
your own color so here's what I think
would be fun so open up a new tab in
your new tab I do a search for color
picker now from color picker what you
can do is so I got a hit this is
Google's color picker what you can do is
you can pick any color you want and
notice down here we're showing you an
RGB value let's say I wanted just like
this perfect shade of purple hottest is
pretty good shade right here well this
specific shade of purple is 128 87 212
so I'm going to take that color and I'm
gonna pop that color into my code and
now my code should show exactly that
shade of purple now this is why we're
using the simulator today because in the
real world it's not exactly the same
shade of purple but that color
combination of red green blue should
show up and make essentially that single
pixel purple it looks like they're and
they're the exact same so pause the
video use a color picker maybe the color
picker that Google had here and pick
your very favorite color and see if you
can make your LED show up in your very
favorite color alright McKinley did you
get yours yeah alright let's see what
you got I'll color did you pick what's
what's Mike Emily's favorite is color in
the whole world so right there this is
McKinley's favorite color in the whole
world
yeah really people instead assign like
the name like turquoise or teal they
should just say that the RGB color
combination do you think it's gonna
catch on yeah alright let's do some more
stuff so that was functions and
functions with arguments now let's learn
about variables variables are important
here's what we need to do so scroll to
the very very top and make yourself a
couple lines above the set up even right
to the very very top so what we want to
do is we're going to make a variable
that's available for the whole program
and the variable is going to be an
integer type variable so int is what you
say whenever you have an integer type
variable and it's gonna be for a red
potentiometer now because I know you
don't like typing much instead of typing
like red potentiometer value I'm going
to call this variable our pot where the
P is a capital P now as you might guess
we're probably gonna have a
potentiometer for green as well as a
potentiometer for blue so let's go ahead
and prepare three variables our pot G
pot and B pot now when you declare a
variable what it does so what is it
variables really works it straight a
variable is a number that your computer
knows about and it can be saved to your
computer and then changed and use later
now there's three steps in a variable
one is you have to declare that it
exists which is what we've done here you
have to somehow set or change its value
and then you have to use it somewhere so
those are kind of the three parts now if
I wanted I could set the variables
initial value right here at the top to
be zero I don't care if you type that or
not because to be honest we're gonna
change it inside of our code so if you
wanted to you could say it's equal to
zero right now or you could leave it off
and it just doesn't matter the important
thing is that we're warning the computer
hey I'm gonna have a variable that I'm
gonna use and here is it today so now
let's go ahead and use this variable
here's what we want to do inside the
loop at the very top line we want to set
our pot to be something and what we want
to do is we want to read on an analog
pin that we haven't made yet we want to
read it so let's go ahead and say analog
read and we're going to wire up a
potentiometer to go to analog value
zero so our pot equals analog read zero
so analog read is a function we've been
learning about functions right analog
read is a function which receives an
argument this argument says hey which
which pin do I want to go read and we're
going to read this one right here it's
it's our a zero cool screen and our a
zero is going to return something now we
haven't had a function returned anything
yet this is a first for us but it's
going to return a number from 0 to 1023
as the range so 1023 1023 is a special
number in binary but we're not going to
get into binary today and that return
value is what the functions can do so
our function so we wrote they say
bullying Boyd is like nothing that's
right
so our functions that we wrote return
nothing but this one actually returns an
integer now let's go make that
potentiometer so that we can actually
read that value and I can get some
numbers so let's go make the
potentiometer so hide the code for a
second and let's go ahead and make a
potentiometer you could search for it
but I actually see the potentiometer
right here so I'm gonna single click on
it over here I'm gonna rotate it and I'm
gonna stick it on my board I'm gonna
stick mine looks like ro8 doesn't really
matter where you put it but I'm gonna
put it kind of up there so they've got
more space in my board and I am gonna
add three of these things so you can
just drag three over or if you like to
do copy paste you can highlight it and
hit control C and then you can hit
control V and pop three of them on there
alright so there they are one two three
ah they're a little crowded towards the
top but that it doesn't really matter
there's gonna be a one more switch
coming later so you can space them out a
little one so here's how 10 Xiamen works
a potentiometer is like a knob right so
like you think of like a sound board has
got all these knobs and these knobs send
a signal to the microcontroller that's
between like 0 to 5 volts and so on the
top of the potentiometer you put what
the highest extreme is so I'm going to
connect it to my red rail so I'm going
to connect it to my red
I'm gonna actually do all three of their
tops first so that says hey when the
when the dial is turned all the way this
way send a five volt signal to my
microcontroller it's really neat it's
like every time you look at a knob for
the rest of your life you'll think about
the fact that you're like just setting
what signal goes to a micro jewelry and
then the bottom goes to ground so if you
turn it the other way it just goes to
ground and then that middle is the
signal that you send to your
microcontroller and so I'm going to take
this top one and I'm going to send it to
a zero and it's going to be controlling
how much juice that one kind of crazy
it's gonna be controlling how much red
there is I hit the shortcut key R that
made my wire go nuts and then this
second one it's gonna go to a one and
since it's gonna be controlling the
greenness I'm gonna turn the wire agree
now again why our colors don't matter it
doesn't matter what color you make the
wires but for the hope of triangle I can
remember which wire does what I like to
make them colors I just to kind of help
me out I'm this bottom one surely you've
picked up on the pattern it's going to
be how much blue value there is which is
going to be the the B pot variable cool
so we've done some wiring and now we're
ready to write some code that actually
uses these these deities so we've
already read our the value off here if
you wanted to run your simulation you
totally could it works but the problem
is is that we've we've declared this
variable our box we've set the value our
pot but we haven't used our pot anywhere
right so that's why that's what we need
to do we need to somehow use that
variable what we're gonna do first is
we're just kind of print it out
that's this just kind of a simple way to
start that way we can kind of see the
value in order to do printing say this
word down here this is serial monitor in
order to do
we have to print things to the serial
ports details I don't want to go into
but in order to use that serial monitor
inside your setup function you need to
do some initialization and here's what
the initialization looks like you need
to type serial dot begin and then you
need to give it some speed I'm choosing
to give it a speed of 9600 now this
function is a little different because
it's inside of a library it's inside of
the serial library so whatever you call
a function inside of the library it's a
little bit more complex so you say
serial note that it has to be a capital
S serial dot begin and so that says hey
call this function begin look for it
inside the Sira library and pass to it
the argument nine six zero zero and that
says how fast to do communication that
actually stands for 9,600 bits per
second details details
now what I want to do is I want to use
my serial library so I'm going to say
serial dot print we're gonna use serial
dot print and we're gonna use serial dot
print L in today and we'll also use them
tomorrow print means display to the
console and println scenes to play it to
the console and then go to a new line so
the first thing I want to do is I want
to just put a little a little label on
here so I'm gonna say your are reading
is so I'm kind of preparing it and then
on the next line I'm gonna actually hit
them with the value so I typed that fast
but you can look at it and then you can
type it as well
so when this works
yeah when not if this works but when
this works here's what's going to happen
it's going to read the analog value the
analog values are from 0 to 1023 right
now it's pointing right at the 0 so it's
going to be 0 to start with but as I
turn this knob so like as I dial it up
this value is going to get closer and
closer to 10 23 now it's interesting
that the voltage is from zero to five
but analog readings display from 0 to
1023 so if it's like two and a half
volts that's right in the middle which
would be like a 512 I will see it once
we get into it and you'll also notice
that here I say print which means like
keep me on the same line and then here I
say println which means like go down to
the next line for the frit next tile so
when you're ready click on start
simulation and then click on serum
monitor here and you can see that it
says R equals and then mines is printing
out a whole bunch of zeros now what I
want to do is I'm going to turn this
knob so I turn it to roughly the middle
of Europe roughly the middle looks like
it's 511 and then if I was to take this
knob and I even kind of like click it
and drag it and I was to turn the knob
all the way up it would show me 10 23
and you can see that there's a lot of
different values in between and the pace
at which it prints I depends on how long
your loop is here so that's why I kept
my loop pretty short so here's the
challenge for you we currently are
reading analog 0 so a 0 right here we're
saving that value off to our pots and
then we're printing it but see if you
can copy these lines of code so this
chunk so make two more copies of it and
modify it so that it prints the red the
green and the blue all on a single line
and then print them and goes to the next
line after so I'm going to pause the
video I'm going to see if you can do
that task all on earth alright so I'm
working on my not done yet so I did what
you probably did is I copied this and I
kind of pasted it two more times
I switched our pop to BG pops I had two
places and then B pot in two places and
then G to be here and the B to be here
now what some people miss this they
forget to change this what pan am I
reading so we want to read pin 0 for red
and then pin 1 and then pin 2 now I
could run it and it'll work now but it
has one
problem one one bun and that's that it
kind of is hard to read because it
prints RGB and RGB it would be better if
they were all printed like on one line
right so our G and B were one line and
the next time it's all online
McKinley do you have any ideas for how
we can make a print all on one line any
ideas
not yet so L n stands for like line so
print line and this L n on this one is
causing it to go to a new line just take
off the Ln this one LM on this one is
making go to a new line so take off that
one as well we only want it in one place
we want it after blue
so after blue prints then go to a new
line it's a Mac and try it again
so now hold by the way you can always
click on clear if you want a clear zero
monitor so now it's displaying the value
of my red green and blue domitor you can
play with the formatting to your heart's
content like it might look better for me
I don't know maybe be in my eyes if I
didn't have a space after the equals but
I had extra space before the the label
doesn't matter right you you decide how
it looks good for you
and then once you've got a system that
you think looks good then you can play
with it now try turning these
potentiometers so if I take red all the
way up I can see that it goes to 1023
if I crank green all the way up I can
see that it gets up to ten twenty three
and then if I take blue all the way up I
can see that it goes to ten twenty three
this is a very good test because if you
are not seeing this then something's
wrong I mean need to fix that before
going on to the next step right so there
are blues in the middle and then here it
loses the bottom but you should be able
to turn these knobs and here I do find
it's actually easier to kind of drag
them around usually I don't drag
anything but if you turn these knobs you
should be able to see the values of
these knobs if you've got that working
then you're ready for the next step if
you don't have that working I do
recommend that you kind of pause I until
it's working right so now what do we
want to do is the next step what I
really want to do is I want to use these
to control my LED right so that I can
like live update what color is so that's
almost going to work almost so here's
what almost works let's go ahead and do
this together take your line of code
where you put in your favorite color and
comment it out and instead type RGB and
the three parameters you're going to
pass in are going to be our pot G pot
and B pots so this is almost going to
work but not point so what this would do
is it would take that potentiometer
value and pass it into your function as
well as your green and your blue now
here's the the one trouble is our pot
potentiometer goes from 0 to 1023 right
or a thousand 23 whereas this function
down here analog right
it only gets values from 0 to 255 so
they're a different range so it's kind
of like if I said hey McKinley gets the
number from 1 to 10 and she says 87
really that's not that's not a valid
range so what we've got to do is this it
is actually only a divided by 4 away
from being in the correct range so
here's what I'm going to do I'm going to
take our pot and before I pass it into
the function I'm going to take our pot
and divide it by 4 and then that is what
I'm going to pass in the function so if
the potentiometer says a thousand that
I'm going to tell the function 250 right
so it's a scaling system so now when I
run it so I hit start simulation
why don't you do is it should use my
potentiometer to decide what color it is
so right now I've got just a little bit
of blue and so that kind of looks purple
needed me but it supposably blue if I
crank blue all the way up you can see I
get a nice crisp blue if I take red and
crank it all the way up I get a purple
and then if I take green all the way up
as well I get a white right if I take
the blue out of the equation red and
green make yellow and it's a neat way to
kind of like play with different color
combinations now to be honest it's
probably easier to play with tools
like the color chooser that you had on
Google but with this like and you can
imagine building it you can turn these
knobs and you can tweak to get whatever
color you want so see if you can get
that together I'm gonna help my camper
out and then we'll move on to the next
step
all right so we're doing good so we've
learned the big picture concept of
functions we've learned the big picture
concept of variables so you saved some
value off and then here we're printing
it and then we're also using it to
control a color I mean we're having a
little fun as well let's go to our next
like big concept encoding and that's def
statements and the idea is we're kind of
showing you some of the big picture
concepts we're not going in depth to
anybody so right now our LED is flashing
and it's flashing because it's being
turned on here and then ruins these
three lines of code to make it flash
right so like let's imagine we had an if
statement or maybe we do those three
lines of code or maybe we don't that
would determine if it's always on or if
it's flashing right so our goal is we're
going to prep our code a little bit is
we're going to say if if some condition
is true now the condition in the middle
here we're going to read some some
analog pin but if some condition is true
then we're going to do some stuff before
I fill in the condition I'm gonna go and
write the rest of this code so if some
condition which I haven't filled in yet
is true then run this code and what
we're going to do is we're going to take
these three lines where it says delay
500 and then off and then delay 500
those three lines we want make it flash
so if some condition is true then do
those lines and then if it's not true
then just don't do them at all and if
you don't know them at all others be
steady on so here's what we want to do
we want to do a digital read of 10 - so
what we're going to do is our condition
is we're going to read 10 - and if Penn
2 is
a high voltage like if it's five volts
if it's a high voltage then it's going
to do this stuff and if it's low voltage
that it won't so let's go ahead and wire
that up and so if statements are very
common in coding ru you type them all
the time and we're just kind of giving
you an example so I'm gonna go do some
wiring so I'm going to temporarily hide
my code so pause the video if you need
so that you can have that code in place
and I'm gonna go do a little wire so
what I want to add this time is a slide
switch so I'm going to click on swap
slide switch and rotate it around and
you can drop it into your board and a
slide switch it's similar to a push
button and then it can go high and low
ease push buttons yesterday the nice
thing about this one is it stays in that
position so you click it and it stays in
that position instead of having to hold
it down what happen and a slide switch
actually works just like a potentiometer
which is kind of funny the top we're
gonna connect to five volts the bottom
we're gonna connect ground and then the
middle we're gonna connect to pin two
and you can make the wire some crazy
color if you want I picked yellow that'd
just be silly also just to be a rebel
I'm just gonna let it shoot straight
across and so a slight switch is
actually very similar to potentiometer
the difference is there's no in-between
values right there's all the way on or
there's all the way off and those words
by the way all the way on all the way
off that means something is digital that
means all the way on all the way off
versus the potentiometers are analog
they can have a range of values that's
what those words digital or really mean
so now let's go ahead and look at our
code and let's predict what's going to
happen so when this switch is at the top
I expect it to be flash because if this
is getting a 5 volts if the switches at
the top expect it to be flashing and
then when it's not at the top I expect
it to be no flashing I just saw it on so
let's go ahead and start the simulation
and sure enough right now my LED is
solid on but as soon as I flip the
switch I should switch to flash
so what we've made here and I know it
seems kind of simple we've made an
Epstein right and if statements are
important in code and if statements
always follow the same pattern or they
have some condition and that abet
condition is true then you run the code
that's inside of there
another thing you couldn't do with if
statements I'm just gonna kind of
mention this you could add an else
statement and this is code that runs if
it's false I don't really have any code
that I want to run if it's false but
maybe I'll stick in just the delay just
for fun right so you don't have to type
this I don't really care if you do or
not but I just wanted to point out that
if it's true you're on this code and
then you can also optionally have an
else to say if it's false didn't run
that right and we'll do some more
complex things with if statements
tomorrow
I don't wanted to show up here so we've
actually have almost all of the major
coding concepts that I wanted to to show
you
we've got functions we've got variables
and we've got 50 that's right so those
are those are the big the big few if I
was gonna add one more and what the heck
we got forgot the interviewed for one
more sissy all right if I was gonna have
one more I'd beat it before let's show
you a forward now I don't
just because my boards already kind of
complex enough I don't want to do
anything on my board I'm just gonna use
the serial monitor to show you a for
loop so here's what I want you to do
find the setup function make sure your
code is not running and make a couple
lines at the bottom of your setup
function and here's what we're gonna do
we're going to type a fool so I'm going
to type it first and then I'm going to
talk about it just because sometimes
it's easier to type the whole thing and
then afterwards we'll talk about it
typing away very quickly
pause the video as you need or you can
do any type as you watching me type but
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
make a for loop and then inside that for
loop I'm going to print something out
and then do a small so pause the video
as you need until you type this and then
let's run it and see what it does so
I don't know when I'll run it first to
see what it does and what this code does
is it counts 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 which
is kind of interesting and then it does
some other stuff let's look at how it
does it
so this is a for loop there's a couple
of different types of loops encoding
there's a forever loop that runs like
forever or there's a for loop that runs
a set number of times and here I'm just
showing you an example of a for loop and
the way this works is it says there's
three clauses in here there's the set up
cause there's the condition clause and
then there's the increment clause and
they're divided by semicolons and this
is just the syntax that C uses every
language is gonna have different syntax
and when it says here is it says hey
start me off with a variable called K
where K is equal to 0 and then it says
keep running this loop so long as K is
less than 10 notice less than if you
wanted it to include 10 you'd have to
say less than oops gotta stop the
simulation for anything less than equal
to and this is read less than or equal
to 10 and then here's the increment it
says after each loops like between every
run of this loop take K and make k equal
to what it was before plus one more so
what I want you to do is I want you to
play with the initial statement the
condition and the increment and see if
you can print different things and then
inside the loop what is doing is it's
just printing the number using
serial.println like we know before and
then I was choosing to make a short
delay if you were to do a bigger number
like 100 or something make sure to make
your delay a little less because
otherwise your program is gonna like
seem to hang until that finishes so here
if I were to go from 0 up to and
including 100 that you could see I did
that pretty quickly you can also change
things like where you say hey it's like
counting my one count by tens right and
so now we just go 0 10 20 30 40 50 60
over left
I so see if you can play with your Lube
a little bit I just to kind of see how
loops work and that's really the end of
this day so we learned about functions
we learned about variables we learned
about if statements and then our last
one here as we learned about loops now
if you decide to spend your life coding
you will use these concepts over and
over and over and over and over again we
just kind of introduced them today in
our next video tomorrow there's a
remote-control car that we'll do
together also if you want to do more
coding there's an extra video for today
that uses an LCD and a servo it's pretty
cool if you want to do that you can it's
optional but we just want you to get
better at coding now one thing that you
will definitely notice about coding is
that it is much pickier when you're
using text versus when you're using
blocks so McKinley I know is sitting
right here next to me McKinley did more
things go wrong when you're coding with
text as compared to coding with blocks
yes do you find that it's very picky on
getting things exactly perfect yes is
that common than expected is it okay and
still fun that's fun so does very honest
answer I appreciate that all right so we
appreciate you you come to code with us
we appreciate you learning text-based
programming there's gonna be more
tomorrow but this is how real software
developers spend their lives and I
wanted to spend some time exposing you
to text-based programming all right see
you next time bye
[Music]